A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Oscar Harkavy FA677
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Oscar Harkavy
1961-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkavy, Oscar
Ford Foundation
FA677
2.62 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Chronological Correspondence Files, 1985-1988
Series II. Speeches, Writings, 1961-1987
Series III. Conference, Meeting Files and Subject Files, 1978-1988
Scope and Contents
Includes correspondence, subject files, correspondence and meeting records as well as a selection of speeches/writings.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Oscar "Bud" Harkavy (1923-2019) was a foundation officer who worked for 35 years at the Ford Foundation. During his time at the Foundation, he worked in its Economic Development and Administration, Population, and Urban Poverty Programs.
Harkavy joined the Ford Foundation in 1953. His work initially focused on the Foundation's program for modernizing business school curricula. From the 1950s to 1962, he was based in the Foundation's Economic Development and Administration Program, moving from Program Associate, to Acting Program Director, to Associate Director. He started his work with the Foundation's population programming in 1963 as Director of the Population Program. Following a change in the Foundation's program organization, the Foundation moved its population programming into its International Division, and Harkavy served as Officer in Charge of that Population Program from 1966 to 1980. Harvaky spent the remainder of his time at the Foundation as a Chief Program Officer in its Urban Poverty Program. He left the Foundation in 1988.
After leaving the Ford Foundation, Harkavy served as a consultant to the Population Council and a Board Chairman for the Population Resource Council. He helped found the Life After the Ford Foundation Society (LAFF) in 1991. He served as LAFF Vice President until 1995 and then as LAFF President for two years.
Harkavy completed his undergraduate education at Columbia College and earned a Master's Degree in business administration and a Ph.D. in economics from Syracuse University.
- Chronological Correspondence Files, 1985-1988; I
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 January (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 February (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 March (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 April (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 May (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 June (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 July (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 August (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 September (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 October (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 November (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1985 December (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 January (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 February (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 March (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 April (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 May (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 June (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 July (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 August (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 September (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 October (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 November (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1986 December (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 January (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 February (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 March (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 April (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 May (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 June (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 July (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 August (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 September (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 October (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 November (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1987 December (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 January (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 February (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 March (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 April (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 May (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 June (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 July (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 August (Box 1)
  - Oscar Harkavy Chron, 1988 September (Box 1)
- Speeches, Writings, 1961-1987; II
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- Incl. Notes and Drafts, 1961-1976 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- "Best Ways to Improve Health in the LDC's" by David Bell and Oscar Harkavy, 1979 February 13 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- Health Issues Paper -- International Division Conference, 1979 February (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- "The Politics of Contraception" by Carl Djerassi, Reviewed by Oscar Harkavy, 1980 April (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- Briefing for Representative Conte Re: International Population Trends, 1980 April 29 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- "Prospects for Improved Contraception" by Atkinson, Schearer, Harkavy and Lincoln in Family Planning Perspectives, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- Testimony, House Committee on Foreign Affairs, Subcommittee on International Economic Policy and Trade -- Population Assistance Programs, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File -- Miscellaneous Speeches and Drafts, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy Speech File, 1981-1987 (Box 2)
  - Population Information Paper -- Related Papers, Notes, Data, 1979 October (Box 2)
  - "Birthspacing: A Common Cause" by Oscar Harkavy in International Family Planning Perspectives, 1986 September (Box 2)
  - "Funding Contraceptive Development" in Technology in Society, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Oscar Harkavy -- Miscellaneous Writings -- Reports, Articles Re: Population and Family Planning, 1969-1976 (Box 2)
- Conference, Meeting Files and Subject Files, 1978-1988; III
  - Family Planning Conference (Jakarta), 1981 April (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Program Review (folder 1), 1986 October 27 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 2), 1986 December 18 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 3), 1987 January 23 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 4), 1987 March 17 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 5), 1987 April 21 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 6), 1987 May 19 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 7), 1987 August 18 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group Meeting (folder 8), 1987 November 17 (Box 2)
  - Children/Families Meeting (folder 9), 1987 March 9 (Box 2)
  - Children/Families Meeting (folder 10), 1987 April 9 (Box 2)
  - Children/Families Meeting (folder 11), 1987 May 13 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Self-Help Meeting -- Social Support (folder 12), 1985 October 18 (Box 2)
  - NGA Conference Panel (folder 13), 1984 October 28-30 (Box 2)
  - Community Epidemiology and Health Management Meeting (Khon Kaen, Thailand) (folder 14), 1988 February 1-4 (Box 2)
  - Developing Countries Review -- Child Survival/Population (folder 15), 1984 (Box 2)
  - Developing Countries Review -- Population, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Child Survival/Population Strategy -- Miscellaneous Papers and Memoranda (folder 16), 1984-1987 (Box 2)
  - Population, Health, Family Planning -- Grant Lists, Financial Control, 1978-1979 (Box 2)